<?xml version="1.0"?>
<root>
  <trials>
    <trial>
      <main>
        <trial_id>RBR-3xf65s5</trial_id>
        <utrn>U1111-1336-7494</utrn>
        <reg_name>REBEC</reg_name>
        <date_registration>19/03/2026</date_registration>
        <primary_sponsor>Universidade Federal de Sergipe</primary_sponsor>
        <public_title>Evaluation of the pharmacist’s follow-up in the management of chronic pain</public_title>
        <acronym> </acronym>
        <scientific_title>Effect of pharmacotherapeutic follow-up in the management of chronic pain: a randomized clinical trial.</scientific_title>
        <scientific_acronym> </scientific_acronym>
        <date_enrolment>01/04/2026</date_enrolment>
        <type_enrolment>actual</type_enrolment>
        <target_size>240</target_size>
        <recruitment_status>Not yet recruiting</recruitment_status>
        <url>https://ensaiosclinicos.gov.br/rg/RBR-3xf65s5</url>
        <study_type>Intervention</study_type>
        <study_design>n/a, randomized-controlled, double-blind</study_design>
        <phase>N/A</phase>
        <hc_freetext>Fibromyalgia; Osteoarthritis; Gout; Rheumatoid Arthritis; Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</hc_freetext>
        <i_freetext>This is a four-arm, partially blinded, randomized controlled trial conducted at the Rheumatology Outpatient Clinic of the University Hospital of Sergipe (Hospital Universitário - Universidade Federal de Sergipe), over 60 months, to evaluate the effect of pharmacotherapeutic follow-up and educational interventions aimed at promoting lifestyle changes among participants with chronic pain. The study will be developed in accordance with the recommendations of the Standard Protocol Items: Recommendations for Interventional Trials (SPIRIT) and will follow the guidelines of the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT). The total number of participants per disease will be 212, equally distributed across four groups in a 1:1:1:1 ratio, with 53 participants per group: Control Group (CG), Group 1 - Pharmacotherapeutic Follow-up (G1), Group 2 - Medication Review (G2), and Group 3 - Health Education (G3). The randomization process will be carried out using an allocation list generated by the Randomizer software, applying stratified block randomization with variable and random block sizes, stratified according to the following variables: sex, age, education level, presence of comorbidities, number of medications in use, and time since diagnosis. Only the supervising researcher, who will not be directly involved in the interventions or outcome assessments, will have access to the allocation list, ensuring blinding of the remaining research team members, including data collectors, data entry operators, and statisticians. Each participant&apos;s allocation will be revealed sequentially, only after confirmation of eligibility and formal signing of the Informed Consent Form (ICF). The seed value used by the software to initiate sequence generation will be recorded, documented, and stored in a secure location. Due to the nature of the intervention, participants in the intervention groups cannot be fully blinded to the pharmacist; however, masking regarding the specific intervention modality received will be maintained, so that participants will not know which subgroup they belong to. Control Group participants will remain blinded to the role of the professional they interact with. Unblinding will only be considered in medical emergency situations, and will be rigorously documented and reported to the Research Ethics Committee in a timely manner. The study will be conducted following the intention-to-treat principle, with recording of any follow-up losses and withdrawals, and application of sensitivity analyses when necessary. All intervention group appointments will take place via pharmaceutical teleconsultation through the WhatsApp® application, chosen for its accessibility, routine use by participants, and end-to-end encryption. Video call teleconsultations will not be recorded by the researchers. The Control Group will receive standard pharmaceutical care, consisting of basic guidance at the time of medication dispensing, with access to the researcher via WhatsApp® for specific medication-related questions, and will have three appointments exclusively for outcome data collection: at baseline, after 4 months, and at the end of 12 months of the study. Group 1 - Pharmacotherapeutic Follow-up will receive a structured intervention over 12 months divided into three phases: Phase 1 - initial assessment (60 to 90 minutes) including analysis of clinical and pharmacotherapeutic data, medication review, medication reconciliation, health screening, lifestyle assessment using the Fantastic Lifestyle Questionnaire, and development of an individualized care plan; second appointment 30 to 40 days later (40 to 60 minutes) for presentation and validation of the care plan, alignment with the responsible physician when necessary, definition of therapeutic goals, and implementation of educational interventions; Phase 2 - longitudinal follow-up with a third appointment 30 to 40 days after the second (30 minutes) to assess initial effectiveness, followed by continuous monitoring for up to 12 months at monthly, bimonthly, or variable intervals according to clinical need; Phase 3 - final appointment at the end of 12 months (30 to 40 minutes) conducted by a data collector pharmacist for review and consolidation of clinical results. Group 2 - Medication Review will receive a structured analysis of clinical and pharmacotherapeutic data with development of an individualized pharmacotherapeutic plan at the first appointment; presentation and validation of the plan with establishment of clinical goals and physician alignment when necessary at the second appointment (30 to 40 days later, lasting 40 to 60 minutes); assessment of the effectiveness of pharmacotherapeutic interventions at the third appointment (30 to 40 days after the second, lasting 30 minutes); and outcome data collection by the data collector pharmacist one month after the third appointment. Group 3 - Health Education will receive a structured analysis of clinical data and responses to the Fantastic Lifestyle Questionnaire with development of a personalized educational care plan at the first appointment; plan validation with educational interventions on clinical condition management and healthy habits, with goal-setting jointly with the participant and, when possible, family members or caregivers at the second appointment (30 to 40 days later, lasting 40 to 60 minutes); assessment of the effectiveness of educational interventions at the third appointment (30 to 40 days after the second, lasting 30 minutes); and outcome data collection by the data collector pharmacist one month after the third appointment. All interventions in Groups 1, 2, and 3 will be recorded and classified according to validated coding systems (Cipolle, Strand, and Morley, 2004; Correr, Otuki, and Soler, 2011).</i_freetext>
        <results_actual_enrolment/>
        <results_date_completed>31/12/2028</results_date_completed>
        <results_url_link/>
        <results_summary/>
        <results_date_posted/>
        <results_date_first_publication/>
        <results_baseline_char/>
        <results_participant_flow/>
        <results_adverse_events/>
        <results_outcome_measures/>
        <results_url_protocol/>
        <results_IPD_plan>No</results_IPD_plan>
        <results_IPD_description/>
      </main>
      <contacts>
        <contact>
          <type>public</type>
          <firstname>Cristiani Isabel</firstname>
          <middlename>Banderó</middlename>
          <lastname>Walker</lastname>
          <address>Avenida Marechal Rondon, s/n, Jardim Rosa Elze</address>
          <city>São Cristóvão</city>
          <country1>BR</country1>
          <zip>49100-000</zip>
          <telephone>+55(79)91935667</telephone>
          <email>bandewalk@hotmail.com</email>
          <affiliation>Universidade Federal de Sergipe</affiliation>
        </contact>
        <contact>
          <type>scientific</type>
          <firstname>Cristiani Isabel</firstname>
          <middlename>Banderó</middlename>
          <lastname>Walker</lastname>
          <address>Avenida Marechal Rondon, s/n, Jardim Rosa Elze</address>
          <city>São Cristóvão</city>
          <country1>BR</country1>
          <zip>49100-000</zip>
          <telephone>+55(79)91935667</telephone>
          <email>bandewalk@hotmail.com</email>
          <affiliation>Universidade Federal de Sergipe</affiliation>
        </contact>
      </contacts>
      <countries>
        <country2>BR</country2>
      </countries>
      <criteria>
        <inclusion_criteria>Patients diagnosed with osteoarthritis, gout, systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, and fibromyalgia; patients of both sexes; aged 18 years or older; currently using prescribed pharmacological treatment for these conditions for at least one month.</inclusion_criteria>
        <agemin>18Y</agemin>
        <agemax>0</agemax>
        <gender>-</gender>
        <exclusion_criteria>Patients with severe psychiatric disorders; cancer; pregnant women; patients without access to the WhatsApp® application; patients currently participating in other clinical trials evaluating the same outcomes of this study.</exclusion_criteria>
      </criteria>
      <health_condition_code>
        <hc_code>C23.888.592.612.274</hc_code>
      </health_condition_code>
      <health_condition_keyword>
        <hc_keyword>Chronic Pain</hc_keyword>
      </health_condition_keyword>
      <intervention_code>
        <i_code/>
      </intervention_code>
      <intervention_keyword>
        <i_keyword>N02.421.668</i_keyword>
      </intervention_keyword>
      <primary_outcome>
        <prim_outcome>To evaluate pain intensity in patients with chronic pain before and after pharmaceutical interventions; assessed using the Numerical Rating Scale (Numerical Rating Scale - 0 to 10); reductions in score will be observed, with a reduction of 10 to 20% considered of minimal clinical importance, a reduction equal to or greater than 30% considered moderately important, and a reduction equal to or greater than 50% considered substantially important. To evaluate the lifestyle of participants before and after pharmaceutical interventions; assessed using the Brazilian adaptation of the Fantastic Lifestyle Questionnaire; changes in total score will be observed, classified into five categories: &quot;excellent&quot; (85 to 100 points), &quot;very good&quot; (70 to 84 points), &quot;good&quot; (55 to 69 points), &quot;regular&quot; (35 to 54 points), and &quot;needs improvement&quot; (0 to 34 points). To evaluate the quality of life of participants before and after pharmaceutical interventions; assessed using condition-specific instruments: Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire Revised - Brasil (Questionário de Impacto da Fibromialgia Revisado para o Brasil) for fibromyalgia (score from 0 to 100, with scores above 50 indicating a major disease impact), Brasil-Arthritis Impact Measurement Scales 2 (Arthritis Impact Measurement Scales 2 - Brasil) for rheumatoid arthritis (score from 0 to 120, where higher scores indicate greater negative impact), Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (Índice de Osteoartrite das Universidades de Western Ontario e McMaster) for osteoarthritis (pain subscale 0 to 20, stiffness 0 to 8, and physical function 0 to 68), and Short Form 36 Health Survey (Formulário Curto de Pesquisa de Saúde com 36 itens) for systemic lupus erythematosus and gout (score from 0 to 100, where higher values indicate better health status).</prim_outcome>
      </primary_outcome>
      <secondary_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>To evaluate pharmacological treatment adherence among participants before and after pharmaceutical interventions; assessed using the General Medication Adherence Scale (Escala Geral de Adesão à Medicação) translated and validated in Brazil, composed of 11 questions on a Likert scale from 0 to 3; adherence categories will be observed: high adherence (30 to 33 points), good adherence (27 to 29 points), partial adherence (17 to 26 points), low adherence (11 to 16 points), and poor adherence (0 to 10 points). To evaluate drug-related problems identified during pharmaceutical interventions; assessed using the classification proposed by Cipolle and colleagues (2004), categorized according to necessity, effectiveness, safety, and compliance, with associated diseases classified according to the International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems - tenth revision (ICD-10); the number and type of drug-related problems identified and resolved throughout the study will be observed. To evaluate participant satisfaction with the pharmaceutical care received at the end of the interventions; assessed using the Net Promoter Score (Pontuação Líquida do Promotor) method, on a scale from 0 to 10; the proportions of participants classified as &quot;promoters&quot; (score of 9 or 10), &quot;passively satisfied&quot; (score of 7 or 8), and &quot;detractors&quot; (score of 0 to 6) will be observed.</sec_outcome>
      </secondary_outcome>
      <secondary_sponsor>
        <sponsor_name>Universidade Federal de Sergipe</sponsor_name>
      </secondary_sponsor>
      <secondary_ids>
        <secondary_id>
          <sec_id>92163625.0.0000.5546</sec_id>
          <issuing_authority>Plataforma Brasil</issuing_authority>
        </secondary_id>
        <secondary_id>
          <sec_id>8.039.148</sec_id>
          <issuing_authority>Comitê de Ética em Pesquisa da Universidade Federal de Sergipe</issuing_authority>
        </secondary_id>
      </secondary_ids>
      <source_support>
        <source_name>Coordenação de aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior </source_name>
      </source_support>
      <ethics_reviews>
        <ethics_review>
          <status>Approved</status>
          <approval_date>09/12/2025</approval_date>
          <contact_name>Comitê de Ética em Pesquisa  da Universidade Federal de Sergipe</contact_name>
          <contact_address>Rua Cláudio Batista s/n B. Sanatório - Prédio do Centro de Pesquisas Biomédicas - HU</contact_address>
          <contact_phone>+55(79)3194-7208</contact_phone>
          <contact_email>cep@academico.ufs.br</contact_email>
        </ethics_review>
      </ethics_reviews>
    </trial>
  </trials>
</root>
